Guide to the Gary Davis collection of Leon Levinstein photographs, 1950s-1970s RL.11358
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gary Davis collection of Leon Levinstein photographs
1950s-1970s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Levinstein, Leon, 1910-1988
RL.11358
1.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes 38 prints
Collection consists of 38 black-and-white photographs taken by Leon Levinstein from the 1950s to the 1970s. The images, usually taken at close range and at unusual angles, portray children, women, and men of all races and backgrounds - many of them marginalized - on New York City streets and on the beach. Locations include Harlem, Manhattan, the Lower East Side, and Coney Island. There are also photographs of people in Haiti. and a few from India and Mexico. Most of the unmounted gelatin silver prints measure approximately 11x14 inches, with several larger prints. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Gary Davis collection of Leon Levinstein photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Gary Davis in 2016 and 2017.
Biographical / Historical
Leon Levinstein (1910-1988) was an American photographer and graphic designer based in New York City. Born in West Virginia, he moved to New York to work in an advertising firm, and studied photography at the New School of Social Research and with the New York Photo League. Most of his time was spent walking the streets of New York City, taking candid shots of people and their surroundings. His work slowly gained wide recognition, and was featured in group shows at the Museum of Modern Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and Limelight Gallery, as well as in many major photography publications. He received a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1975.
Content Description
Collection consists of 38 black-and-white photographs taken by Leon Levinstein from the 1950s to the 1970s. The images, usually taken at close range and at unusual angles, portray children, women, and men of all races and backgrounds - many of them marginalized - on New York City streets and on the beach. Locations include Harlem, Manhattan, the Lower East Side, and Coney Island. There are also photographs of people in Haiti. and a few from India and Mexico. Only one scene, a piano in a room, has no people in it.
Levinstein deliberately left his images untitled and undated, thus most prints in this inventory are accompanied by content descriptions created by a collector or dealer, or, in a few cases, by library staff. Almost all the prints bear a photographer's stamp on the back and a few are signed by Levinstein. Most of the prints measure approximately 11x14 inches, with a few larger prints; in the dimensions given, height precedes width.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
City dwellers -- Portraits; Documentary photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Urban life -- Photographs; Coney Island -- New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Haiti -- Photographs; Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; India -- Photographs; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Portraits; Mexico -- Photographs; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Levinstein, Leon, 1910-1988
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0001)
  Scope and Contents
  Child walking next to woman pushing baby carriage. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1230
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0002)
  Woman with young boy under umbrella. Later print, resin-coated paper. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1242
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0003)
  Woman with baby carriage. Later print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1293
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0004)
  Man with sand on his bare back. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1538.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0005)
  Taking in the sun. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1676.
- East Harlem, circa 1960 (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0006)
  Girl in striped dress. Vintage print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1687.
- Lower East Side, 1957 (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0007)
  Child in white ruffled dress. Title and photographer's signature on back. Later print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1928.
- East Harlem, 1953 (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0008)
  Crowd of kids in front of window, little girl with straw. Vintage print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1930.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0009)
  False leg in street. Vintage print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1933.
- Los Angeles, 1975 (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0010)
  Piano in room with blackboard. Vintage print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1934.
- No known title, 1950s (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0011)
  Father and child lying on beach. Printed on thin black board. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2189.
- Lower East Side, 1956 (Box 1, Image RL.11358-P-0012)
  Child in white ruffled dress. This is the same subject but different shot as previous image in collection, but is labeled on back with 1956 instead of 1957. Later print. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2419.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s; 10 7/8 x 12 3/4 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0013)
  Street scene in front of ethnic stores, New York City. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1222.
- No known title, 1970s?; 13 5/8 x 10 5/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0014)
  Man, seated, with Panama hat on knee, Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1217.
- No known title, 1970s?; 14 x 11 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0015)
  Man, standing, hand on chin, Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1263.
- No known title, 1960s?; 14 x 11 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0016)
  Man sitting on stoop, cup in hand, New York. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1317.
- No known title, 1960s-1970s; 11 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0017)
  Man lying on steps in street, New York. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1355.
- Lower East Side, circa 1953; 11 x 14 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0018)
  Man with cigarette in holder and woman with veil seen through window of car, New York. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1512.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s; 11 x 12 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0019)
  Three women sitting in chairs on street, New York. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1513.
- No known title, 1967; 13 1/4 x 10 3/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0020)
  Two men standing in front of concrete pier at beach, night, Coney Island? Mounted on black board. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2102.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s?; 14 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0021)
  Men and women sitting in a row on park lawn. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1917.
- No known title, 1950s-1960s; 11 x 14 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 2, Image RL.11358-P-0022)
  Woman putting on eye makeup. Mounted on black board. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1424.
- No known title, circa 1955; 10 x 13 5/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0023)
  Older man and woman lying on the beach, Coney Island. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2408.
- No known title, undated, 11 x 14 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0024)
  Man standing with back to camera, looking at artwork on gallery walls. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2183.
- No known title, undated, 13 7/8 x 10 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0025)
  Man, with eyes closed, leaning against metal scaffold. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2153.
- No known title, 1960s-1970s; 13 1/2 x 10 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0026)
  Woman with umbrella and two cigarettes walking on sidewalk, New York. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2263.
- No known title, undated, 10 3/4 x 9 1/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0027)
  Older man in hat with striped band, Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2394.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 11 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0028)
  Man looking out of window of hut, Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2366.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 11 1/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0029)
  Man in straw hat pulling cart, Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1416.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0030)
  Smiling man lying back in small cab, India. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC1527.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0031)
  Young man, seated, preparing to have his portrait taken by street photographer, India. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2204.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0032)
  Man in suit, tie, and straw hat, holding book up, "Reveillons nous," Haiti? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2214.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 11 1/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0033)
  Street barber shaving customer, India. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2362.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 10 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0034)
  Man in suit and tie, lifting hat while opening door, Mexico? Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2378.
- No known title, 1970s; 14 x 11 1/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0035)
  Street dentist or doctor examining a squatting man's teeth, India. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2357.
- No known title, 1970s; 8 1/2 x 12 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 3, Image RL.11358-P-0036)
  Large group of men and women on board a boat, Haiti. Mounted on black board. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2126.
- No known title, undated, 16 3/4 x 13 1/4 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 4, Image RL.11358-P-0037)
  Man in beret and hand behind his back, by the roadside. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2026.
- No known title, undated, 8 1/2 x 12 7/8 inches; Gelatin silver print (Box 4, Image RL.11358-P-0038)
  Blurry shot of polo match. Mounted on black board. Legacy id (assigned by collector): GDC2126.